everybody buddy here and welcome welcome
John back to the server which as you can
see is is bustling
we've MIDI that's great there I'm very
happy to be here again and Tyler's gonna
be recording this session I'm Tyler did
you start already or hey yeah we're hey
John welcome good to hear you too we are
recording and we just cut off whatever
we needed post-production so thank you
everyone for being here so welcome to
the awaking from the meeting crisis
discord and our bi-weekly Q&A with John
Verve a key who is the inspiration for
for us all being here on this server and
and yeah the server's been bustling
we've had quite a bit of activity a lot
of chatting
we've got three events this week
including this one we've got
so today's John John's to be answering
questions tomorrow at at 1:00 Eastern
we've got Paul Van Der clays coming by
that's great yeah you're welcome to come
to John if you'd like I'm sure everybody
would love the two of you together you
don't have and and then Wednesday we've
got Greg Henriques coming for a Q&A
great people yeah it's it's been great
you know we've having these bringing in
your voices with for Vicky's guests and
it seems like a nice way of bridging the
work that you're doing sure with the
work here hopefully get Jordan on here
to Jordan Hall that'd be amazing
yeah that would be great I'll reach out
to him as him as well and and oh we can
sit yeah - a lot - a lot of people so it
yeah so this has been great
so thanks John for being here so we've
got a bunch of people here we'll ask
people so please note that we are
recording this and we'll be uploading it
to YouTube later we can open it up
actually maybe I can start off with a
question that we've been talking about
in our meditation Sangha we've been
we've been meeting just so everyone
knows we've been well while John does
his morning meditation with rebecky few
of us have been meeting here on the
discord at 9:30 Eastern and we'll do the
meditation and then chat about our
experience after and and one question
we've been trying to figure out is with
meta so you've described the you've
described a mantra with these three
these three parts so you know may may X
be happy and healthy
may I recognize X is true suchness and
may I see the morning X and so we've had
two questions about this the first
question is when we're doing this mantra
is do we pick one of those or or is it
going through each three those are
different formulations picked one and I
gave people different ones so they could
experience
experiment to see which one starts to
resonate or work and it'll probably
shift around at different times too so
but yet pick one of them and then do it
for sure
okay thank you that that answer is a
that answers that and and and the other
thing I guess is we were trying to
figure out what is the difference
between suchness and morna's okay which
they have a non logical like identity
that's kind of one of the claims of all
the you know of all of these mystical
wisdom traditions you know fun as it is
Brahman I just think I'm so I could be
very careful about distinguishing them
but the difference in the way I'm using
it is that the morning to
the fact that everything like the
reality is sort of common in the toilet
explosive the amount of information out
there ISM is both qualitatively and
qualitatively beyond any any you know
any final framing it's always there's
always going to be more than anything be
afraid and that's what I that's against
the morning the not that such nests have
to do much more with the fact that there
is a way in which every determinant
thing or entity has a uniqueness to it a
way in which it's individuated and
instantiated that resists categorization
it used to be in the medieval
scholastics is called the you know like
the quiddity of it I believe or
something like that
the idea is that if I subtract from you
all the way all that about you for long
can be grasped categorically there's
that about you in which all of those
categorization in here English they in
here so morning is about sort of the
ultimate mystery about how you connect
and participate in things beyond
yourself such this is the mystery of how
you are a non repeatable unique
instantiation that therefore because of
that uniqueness and non repeatability is
not that is not properly part of any
category
it's the non categorical uniqueness
presence here now NIST's instantiation
of you or of anything right so it's a
it's not just a cat a property of people
I mean so when you with part of what our
verb does in fact is it can remind us
about you know you're saying that the
painting of the shoes by then go right
right you could you you pick up on
there's something yeah their shoes and
their old shoes but there's something
unique and non-repeatable about them and
that's what
work of art is reminding us reminding
you with a suchness of issues but work
of art works of art can also remind you
right about they can open you up to a
sense of awe suchness gives you a sense
of intimacy of deep connectedness to the
intimacy of something it's like it's
pure presence to you whereas whereas
mortis tends to put you into more
relationships of awe as you sense of
connectedness to that which always
transcends you was that helpful very
helpful yes thank you thank you very
much for that that that was exactly I
think that was exactly one of what I
know I was looking for if I could follow
up on that can can we map suchness and
more nests on to heidegger's critique of
Anto theology in that suchness is kind
of the proper goal of ontology and more
nests is the proper goal of theology as
long as you're doing is right you're
picking up on yeah how that how you
trying to break out of both the Anto and
the theology side of the arco theology I
take it that you're trying to do right
is that what you're trying to do right
exactly that then I'd say yes I think I
think you're yeah I hadn't made that
connection so can I congratulate Your
Honor I think that's very very good yeah
I like that a lot
very cool thanks for following up there
thank you
all right so we can
it up for four questions if these
questions can be basically just so you
know can be on on anything related to
all this I mean if you have questions
from the series from leaking from the
meaning crisis series from any of John's
videos to any of the topics he covers so
so use use the opportunity that John's
given us to ask all those questions that
that that you've been thinking of and
haven't had a chance I'm also very
interested in questions I don't like to
call them practical because the word
practical is taken on a weird me I call
them practicable questions questions of
practice so like like you did right from
the meditation with contemplation series
or you know you know all the stuff I'm
doing with other people around dialectic
and dialogue cultivation of wisdom you
know I mean I'm interested in those
kinds of questions as well so just to
make it clear that you know from the
very practicable to the you know most
philosophical I'm really open to any
questions anywhere in between and
including jump in in yeah I kiss it hi
John that was very impressed with the
way that you spoke to Paul after our
previous Q&A so that was amazing and
also well thank you you were helped you
were helpful you were helpful thank you
well glad to be of service I'm hopefully
I can can be more helpful and I also
wanted to just say that the you made a
distinction between potentiality and
possibility in your recent talks and I'm
very enthusiastic about that I think
that's a good move as well my question
is if I remember correctly you have
information in your physical ontology do
I have that right yes I think I've been
from it yeah you need yeah well III
distinguish the two two kinds of
information there's okay information
which is part of the physical ontology
and then there's n information which is
meaningful information
and the hope is that we'll be able to
explain the latter in terms of the
former within sort of cognitive science
that it just important because there's a
lot of sloppy talk and fire out there
that equivocates between those two
senses and it really really unhelpful
may never okay um yeah I just want to
follow on an that maybe you can you also
help me to clarify between the two
common kinds of me information sure my
question is basically well I think it is
the case that if you have information in
your physical ontology that you have to
have some kind of formal cause within
your physics and I was wondering if you
agree with that or if you disagree and
you see a way around it no no I think
that's I think that's right so let's
talk about the sort of the I mean
there's lots of we can get it some at
math which let's avoid that the basic
sense of you know of the Shannon sense
of information and then integrating that
with signal detection theory is the idea
that you like a signal is a
probabilistic relation so if the
probability of a given B E is greater
than the probability of a on its own
that B is a signal for a but B is a
informative signal if B's prediction of
a helps you rule out alternatives to
which they belong so if they belongs to
a set of like seven other things that
could have happened and B predicts a
that's quite informative because you've
ruled out all the alternatives and in
that sense information information is
pervasive in the universe because it's
just that probabilistic predictive
relationship but notice the language
that I'm using right and right I'm using
the language of you know probabilistic
relationships and the ruling of the
vaulter which is also a probability term
and I think you're going to have to
ultimately ground that in some kind of
formal causation yeah I think so I would
agree with that some countries
editability so
that yeah that's that's exactly right
and so I want to be really careful here
and I know as I know you do too because
part of what we're doing with it
no I don't think intelligibility is an
equivocation between the two kinds of
meaning I think it's a proper bridge the
trouble I have is that not enough
when people talk about intelligibility
I'm trying to be very careful here it's
wrong but when you people talk about
intelligibility they often fall into
that equivocation between those two
kinds of meeting you don't I mean so I
think the concept of intelligibility is
really really important that there's a
structure or there's a there's a
structure that makes there's a structure
of T information that appropriately
affords the generation of M information
and that's what we're trying to get at
and that's why I'm really interested in
the ancient idea of logos precisely
because it was an attempt an attempt to
talk about that affordance as bridging
between the writings yeah well I've got
a long-term plan to associate the formal
course with your perspective of knowing
so yeah this is a good mood a good
answer for first ones I'm convinced okay
I just want that was very hopeful for me
that you know there's a lot of talk
about sense making right now and this is
good a culture needs it but I think we
need to be very careful about you know
getting very careful about using terms
like intelligibility in terms like
information there's a lot of ways in
which we can fall in very confused and
confusing thinking and so we need to
really care around this yeah and I
mentioned the Cartesian dualism is also
quite a thorn in your side and mr.
garden yes yeah but there's some very
interesting stuff happening with a lot
of people right now so yeah great I've
got more questions but I want to give
other people a chance oh that was an
excellent question thank you for that
I'm continuing to find your questions
and I mean this in the good sense of the
term very thought-provoking well that's
great that's exactly what I mean
thanks John happy mask salesman I think
you were trying to get in before yes
that's right thank you I have a question
and I will best try to articulate it I
don't know if it's fully fleshed out in
my mind but nonetheless I will ask him
to what extent do people other do
thoughts opinions conversations that
you've had with other people say in the
day guide or influence your meditation
practice do you ever fight yourself
reflecting on on events during the day
throughout that practice and is that
something that you try to shut out or do
you invite into the meditation yeah so
that's an excellent question that's
often why I give novices the advice of
not meditating right after having an
emotionally engaged conversation it's
like I used to call it what it used to
make sense to people you're playing the
tapes in your head so yeah one of the
things you want to do is you want to try
and treat that like a distraction label
it and yeah and try to return to the
breath yeah don't try and force it out
try and make your breath more attractive
in the ways I talked about in the course
as a strategy now what you should do
right is you should then so that's sort
of one side of the other side is it you
should think about taking up a practice
in which you properly respond to that
and one of the things that's important
to do with that that I try to do is to
try to move it from room ination which
is running in your head to journaling
where you write it down and you you sort
of get into like almost like a written
dialogue with the person you don't have
to write names like I say this and they
say that but you sort of write write it
out it's a lot of research showing that
you know the simple act of doing that
move of journaling and writing it allows
you to move to the third-person
perspective at times get the Soliman
effect often notice patterns that you
can't notice when you're keeping in and
working memory
and this actually helps that that that
inner conversation turned into almost
like a a proper practice of dialectic in
which you're starting to actually
challenge anything ant is the knees
famously said that when they asked him
what he learned from Socrates and he
said this in a way that was meant to be
very provocative as he learned how to
converse with himself he learned how to
do this he learned how to take the
interactions with Socrates and then
properly do them on his own and so I
recommend doing a two prong strategy I
recommend but in the sitting right and
then treat it like a distraction ing
word return to your breath switch really
try to renew your interest in the breath
make it more salient to you all the
stuff I talked about but also take up a
practice where you say no what I'm going
to do you can even talk to that part of
you that wants to play the tapes and say
I'm gonna give you your due and but
we're not just gonna run the tapes we're
actually gonna work this through we're
gonna we're going to actually turn this
into an interactive form of reflection
and restructuring of thinking so I would
recommend that as as a response thank
you very much that was very helpful
you're welcome come could I get in next
so about a year ago I realized that a
lot of my problems had come from an
internet addiction and so I found it
very interesting
when I heard you talk about the
opposition between Anago gay and
addiction so I was just wondering
whether you can either tell me immediate
steps one could take to halt the
addictive process and turn it round to a
mark okay or tell me someone who can
tell me like a book or something well I
think spices game could you throw in a
definition of a negau gay for everyone
if you if you could well while you're
answering that
so and magog a is its electronic form
that's the opposite of what the
reciprocal name of it so but it has more
than just the reciprocal opening because
it it talks about well Plato talks about
two important aspects so the let's talk
about sort of the inner inner aspect of
an a dog a is properly aligned in the
different components of the psyche
learning how to create an inner culture
by which they are self-organizing in a
mutually optimizing fashion rather than
being beset by internal anxiety and
inner conflict and then the idea from
that at is that actually reduces the
degree to which you're subject to
bullshitting yourself and self-deception
and then that affords you picking up on
patterns in the world that outward you
that you would not seen before because
of your self-deception and as you pick
up on those patterns you get actually
better at distinguishing real patterns
from illusory one and then you
internalize that ability and that right
and you then look for patterns within
the psyche you've developed a taste for
patterns of it more real and then that
helps you notice better deeper patterns
within the psyche that helps you further
optimize and that reduces the
self-deception he's come were able to
realize real patterns in the world and
the whole thing was separately opens the
world is opening up you're getting
deeper and deeper into the real patterns
as it is then it called them and at the
same time you're getting sort of deeper
and deeper into the real patterns within
the psyche and you're satisfied with
cyclical opening year simultaneously
satisfying the meta desire to be at
peace and to have a fullness of being
and the meta desire to be in contact
with reality a conforming transform in
contact with Valerie
so that's an acog it's sort of
reciprocal opening that is also
cultivating
wisdom but it also has the accents of a
sense of love you tend to in that
reciprocal opening you start falling in
love with the depths of things that's
Anna gar game
and the person that asked me the
question is you know it's right to see
and I kind of the reverse the way out of
addiction I think of addiction as the
primary form of self-deceptive is the
self-destructive behavior within
participatory learning and so the thing
a book I would recommend you do is for
reading marks book marklar memoirs have
an addictive brain and you can see
someone spiraling it and then you know
it's so you want to read some of his
work and then for reciprocal opening for
Soriano could you get them okay the
person is yes what Mark Lewis mark Lewis
the book is entitled memoirs of an
addicted brain
he's the neuroscientist he's the guy
that is proposing the model of addiction
as reciprocal narrowing and when I was
talking to mark I was saying but if
there's reciprocal narrowing there's
also reciprocal opening that's the
Martha talking about Mark Lewis and the
book is memoirs of an addicted brain and
then if you want to get into like the
things that will get you into and agog a
sort of the fastest right are real world
flow induction things right like you
know playing jazz or rock climbing or
doing a martial art you've got to get
into something that can get you into the
flow state but not just in the virtual
domain because I could get hijacked
right you got to do it into the main
when you're really wrestling with the
causal structure of the world and you
have to transform be in relationship to
it so you know you know chicks at my
highest book finding flow
Jamie wheels for stealing fire those
kinds of things would be helpful to
start them if you'd sort of did both of
those that might help you get I think
what you're looking for
was very helpful yeah I'll take that
yes any who else has a has a question I
have a question concerning the
meditation series and this discord so
well I was wondering if you had any
prescriptions or other thoughts
concerning how we can best support each
other in practice in the meditation
group this meeting on this discord and
in general yeah I mean what's happening
in the Sangha and the chat group is
really good and this is what I see
happening it in saying I said why people
ask questions of each other they share
problems things that are you know things
that are finding obstacles or hindrances
they also share things that are helpful
things nuances of practices or things
they've read or looked at that are
helping them with the practice also you
should make it part of it to celebrate
not in any sort of self aggrandizing way
but people should bring moments where
they just say hey I had this moment of
insight or I had this moment where I
really feel really well fitted or I was
able to really see through what a
pattern that are normally locked into
and so you know those things you know
you know bringing that in those moments
of celebration the moments where you
found things that afford the practice
the obstacles you're finding in the
practice also anything it's unclear to
you questions you might have a
clarification those third those are sort
of the main things you want to be doing
and then finally just just a sense of
you know encouraging people because
everybody's motivation waxes and wanes
and one of the things we can rely on a
distributed cognition with other
people's motivation being stronger when
our is is weaker and vice versa and so
that's very very important to that that
element of of encouragement thank you
that incidence that helps along if there
is a space could I ask a follow-up on
the same topic that's fine with me so
this morning after this sit we we
practice Lexi Oh Davina individually and
discuss it afterwards I know some church
groups do this as a group practice and
something we were discussion and
wondering about is how to adapt the
version of it then you've presented on
to a group practice such as on this
discord yeah I think that's excellent I
mean I think ultimately that I think
people should be doing Lexi OH both
individually and part of what sorry
sense promise area but part of what I
would like help sort of help people to
build and something I'm trying to work
on myself and trying to understand so
there's very much work in progress is
how you could have group Alexio and then
how that would lead into something
naturally like the Ilocos where people
would start talking about it in a
dialogical fashion and trying to see how
those would fit together
um is sort of optimal in my mind I I
think for doing it at least trying to do
it at least intuitively is you know pick
and you should cycle right people should
take turns one but up would you live in
the in the group sitting I would have
one person do the two readings share
their personal resonances and then other
you know everybody sort of do the
practice initially within themselves and
then like like a bit of a deal logos
everybody share what their residences
were and how they unfolded it and be
really open right you know this isn't
any kind of comparison or in a sense of
contrasting but everybody share you know
how they resonated how they enacted
what's disclosed what came out of it and
and then you're gonna have you know
nuances of perspective and the I
collectively to try and create a very
rich shared salience landscape about all
the different aspects and try and
provoke each other you know you know and
try to be open and said oh I hadn't
thought about that
that brings out an aspect that I didn't
get when in my own take on Alexio and
see what would it mean to try and
internalize that into your perspective
and vice versa that's what I would see
happen happening in a group city thanks
for that chunk so as it happens I'm I'm
trying to draft a structure right now
for a group of luck to you a Davina
practice that I'll propose tomorrow and
I'm also thinking along the same lines
and I'm wondering if some of this stuff
from circling and the intersection
between circling and deal overs can be
incorporated I see them being almost
almost on a continuum where the Alexia
will just shade naturally is that the
right word into you the DM logos and
then the D Lobos will also refer berate
backwards when people are giving their
Lexia that's exactly as I see it that's
why I see the Lex heel is bridging
between Lex between de logos and and the
and the mindfulness practices so maybe
in in future in some future Q&A I might
follow up with you on with further data
after we've tried this a few times I
would really love to know that please
please serious requests on my part you
need like we're running all kinds of you
know in suits you you know in formal
experiments on necklace and all the
feedback you can all get and give to
each other to make this work is really
really important please do that please
alright I'll be sure to thank you
question please so in our Lexy o Divino
class this morning I'm realizing that
you're going to find found a mystery
school of wisdom at some point down the
road because that's your Tay and you
love it but I was doing some research on
the Ponte Shaw's and trying to find the
best translation of that and you know
you didn't say how long to read and like
three aravind those mystic fire is like
500 pages so I might be working now and
for ages and then theor G and the soul
might be okay for my narrative or my
essay oh the shop up the shot book is
excellent I highly recommend it oh okay
and it was interesting and doing my
research that a lot of scholars through
the ages have fought the noses have the
been dontoh deity that one guy said that
the Brahma has conceived in the upon
assad's and defined by some cars clearly
the same as the noses so the standard
yeah and Max next Muir says something
and let's see yeah so I guess he had no
connection with the Hindu edition but
yet they're saying he's if he would have
his system would in all probability mark
a last phase of the Venn danta
philosophy which is a pretty big
actually for that so what of his works
if I wanted to just read a few things of
Spinoza have the clear connection with
the bathtub oh boy that's really first
of all yeah
yeah I think I think I well I don't know
yeah how do you may I think the sort of
could not do old interpretation Spinoza
which is very much like what you're
saying and I'm trying to I think the the
reason why there's similarities to ism
Spinoza is obviously very influenced by
purpose and the whole Neoplatonic
condition many people have noted there's
some deep connections between not
necessarily historical connections
connections in terms of what you might
call discoveries or invent here easy
attic wisdom traditions DT Suzuki was
very fond of 20 that I opened the gilda
school also has have to answer your
question let me see let me think about
this there is a couple I mean the ethics
is ultimately the thing that has to be
read and you have to read the accurate
the XX both as an argument and almost
like Lexi o Divina
in order to really get it and and I've
done that a couple times in that'll take
you like a year to read through the
ethics properly and I don't know if
there's anything sort of it his earlier
essay hang on a sec I'm just
there's an there's an earlier thing
that's much that's much smaller it's
sort of like a precis
and it's called his short Spinoza's
short treatise on God man and human
welfare and was he too interesting
yes vanozza short treatise on God man
and human welfare and and you'll find
that that the ethics is I mean the
ethics is profound and you should always
end up in the ethics but you'll find
that this is more lyrical and more
accessible and therefore maybe at least
initially more amenable to Alexio Davina
what's interesting about this tokheim
tradition same thing you get when you're
reading for eNOS or ProQuest you on one
hand here getting text that is very very
like almost it's Socratic and its
ability to you know it's argumentation
and challenging you conceptually but at
the same time it's a spiritual exercise
that's doing all this other
transformative stuff that can be picked
up on in the Alexio Divina but that's
what I would recommend
Spinoza short treatise on God man and
human welfare I was just going to find
my copy because I'm trying to find the
publisher of it because I got it I just
downloaded it from sorry I've ordered I
didn't download it in order to comb
Amazon but it it just seems to be a
direct frantic so I think it's in public
domain and it's just been cool so you
might be able to it was very inexpensive
I mean so I would recommend that I would
recommend that thank you
hi John I have a question yes please
okay so I was just wanna give me a
cognitive science account effect so I've
been reading a book called shame and
pride by David Nathanson I'm not sure if
you've heard of that book anyways and he
tries to argue in the book that effect
is is an eternal amplification of a
stimulus of an environmental stimulus so
and then young girl fear I know you've
got a lot of talks with with Todd
Anderson about this yeah Anderson Todd
and young makes a comment about a fact
saying the effects occur where
adaptation is weakest
so again can you just give me a call my
cognitive science account on what effect
is please yeah so the amplification of
stimuli because I'm only is picking up
on the attentional aspects of a fact
they affect constrains reshapes the stop
organization I think it's I don't think
that's a sufficient account of what
affected so good a good place to look is
like DiMaggio's for Descartes Sarah when
he argues that part of the role of
effect it's not just amplification
there's selection prioritization and
then there's the wreckage there's the
there's a project of affording the
organism to appropriately shape itself
in order to anticipate its environment
so I would bring up I would bring that
out to you know adaptive anticipation
and maybe that's picking up a bit of
young and this is coming out in the in
the predictive processing models that
are becoming very dominant and others
then what that is doing is basically
telling you how well your
dissipation of the world is going that
you know you're sort of modeling the
world that's translating into landscape
and then that's telling and then how
well is that getting you to actively not
imaginatively but in action anticipate
your environment and positive effect is
basically saying is it's sort of
feedback saying you're actually doing
better this homing in on getting better
at you know inactive anticipation in the
environment and negative effect is oh
right your salience landscaping you're
not paying attention to the right thing
and you're not you're not activating the
right skills right and you're not you're
not anticipating the right causal
structures you're not picking up on the
right patterns so that's how I would
that's how I base it on the work that's
coming out the process and model the
work that's coming out of some of the
best neuroscience around a fact and and
this lines up with a lot of stuff I do
on relevance realization and salience as
well as work that out of on attention so
I would put all those together that's
how I would that's what I would say
perfect is doing yeah to comment on what
you said about predictive processing
Nathanson gives you an example in the
book about a little girl that takes her
daddy's papers and she begins to without
him knowing and she begins to rip them
up rip them up right and she's playing
with them and then her dad comes in and
then she's expecting in a
phenomenological sense right that she's
done something right she does she her
playing by airplane and her dad responds
by yelling at her right so and then and
then Madison says that's when Shane
that's a shame happens essentially my
habit is that you it's as if there's a
suppression of your effect your effect
is being redirected because it has
essentially the positive feelings have
nowhere to go
um it's it's too quick of a change in
the in in in the environment so but
thank you for that yeah yeah I mean I
would you want that at least and say
well what's happening is right you know
she's
is a quick sequence of effect there's
something like disappointment and then
there's something probably like fear and
what that what's that saying is maybe if
you allow me to use some of my language
met the frame the framing that she had
but she was playing right is not picking
up on like the problems trying to solve
which is how to have an appropriate
connection to her dad and so yeah what
what the athlete is doing is it's trying
to rapidly restructure or salience
landscaping and her framing so that the
the goal that she most cares about has a
greater chance of being dissolved yeah
that makes a lot of sense thank you
thank you for that yeah
I think if I could just riff on that for
a second you know this is a theme that
other I mean I was just talking to
somebody Mark Miller is really great
where he three users coming out of in
Clarks lab all the stuff that the idea
that we're going to get sophisticated
cognition intelligence and it not have
you know very powerful complex up
organizing a fight I think that's a
misplaced project I think that's a very
misplaced project I think effective
cognition and intelligent cognition are
very deeply intertwined in
interdependent and for very good reason
so I'm open to more questions that
please I had a question about the
medication so I you know I see a lot of
a lot of resonance with meaning crisis
work that you're doing and the
meditation and so to some extent it
looks like these two things are acting
in concert with one another and so I'm
wondering like did the meditation inform
the meaning crisis or vice versa you
know yeah with dialog are they in and
and what's sort of your intention for
the meditation in relation to the
meaning crisis like how do you see that
fitting together okay so first of all I
want to thank you for that that that's a
very that dialogue is intense and trying
to properly convey that to people so
it's practicable for them it's exactly
one of my goals so you you're I'm being
encouraged by unit noting that and
seeing that connection because the
dialogue is it's very symmetrical it
goes both ways they're mutually
informing each other very very deeply
now to the just thank you for that okay
that's very encouraging to me it's very
encouraging to me the the the
relationship between them is well I mean
first of all there's you know proximal I
think and I don't have time to repeat it
here but there's a lot of the choices
with verve a keys recently I've been
building this argument I think ovid the
Cova crisis is really increasing Dhamma
side really accelerating the meeting
crisis for a large number of people and
I think just giving them the meditation
is to try and give them not anything
that's a symptom suppressant but
something that really deeply connects
them in a transformative way you know to
to the perspectival and the
participatory machinery that needs to be
re access reactivated restructured in
order to give people both both the
response to you know self-deception and
also the capacity to enhance the
connectedness that's at the core of the
sense of meaning in life so that's the
sort of proximal thing
the long-term relationship is that I see
the ecology of practices that you know
because I there's a meditative practice
there's a contemplative practice there's
now alexia practice obviously is that
they're trying to argue that should
merge in with the dialectic practice and
then there's all the movement practices
and there's other self examination
property this ecology is right and both
how it can be practiced individually and
collectively and and we're all working
on this right now together and I thank
you all for that this this is that that
dialogue in that connection that's the
beating heart of what I think the what I
want I'm trying to get at with the
religion that's not a religion that
that's the long term sort of project
immediately wanted speedy people real
responsive resiliency to the way in
which the Kovach crisis is exacerbating
and accelerating the vini crisis for
very many people is that helpful I yeah
that was that was that was pretty
helpful I'm just I'm sort of wondering
where you see meditation in particular
slotting in because you can still be
subject to self-deception Wow oh oh well
because I don't think you should never
just meditate you should be doing
meditation and contemplation but you
should also be practicing active open
mindedness that's what I meant by other
self-examination things you should also
be practicing like the dialogic practice
so that you have to learn how to deal
with confront internalize the
prospective perspective of others I mean
you have to get you have to do many of
these practices for many of the kinds of
knowing for the many different ways in
which we could fall prey to
self-deception I think I think I would I
would argue it's a mistake to try and
sort of CD from just I want to say this
very careful because I don't want to say
the one thing I think it would be a
mistake to try and see from just within
a meditative practice how you might be
falling prey to self-deception within
meditation I don't think anyone
this is completely self-corrective in
that matter we shouldn't confuse the
fact that these practices help us to
self-correct with assuming that these
practices are comprehensively
self-corrective this is a mistake I see
a lot because these practices are so
good at helping us as individuals
self-correct many people assume that
these practices are completely
self-correcting and self-sufficient and
I think that's a deep mistake that's a
that's an equivocation it's a deep
mistake that has to be addressed by
noting all of these practices have
respective strengths and weaknesses and
we have to distinguish between the way
in which a practice is helping me be
self corrective from the degree to which
the practice itself can be something
corrected those are not the same thing
that was the that was an interesting
observation so that this gets back to
the seeing through versus looking at and
yeah but that's what I was looking for
Thanks that really clarifies it I
appreciate that thank you thank you that
was an excellent question
winter if I can throw
a question about about language I say
you've given us a great grammar
vocabulary through your your series and
after and I think that's it's very very
useful one thing we've been talking
about a little bit here in the forum is
you know there are times where you come
up with new words like religio and there
are times where you I think in in your
recent talk with Paul van der clay you
said you reinvent show a word so you
recalibrate the definition like like
you've done with soul one concern I I
have with that is that it can cause
confusion firstly when talking to people
who have you know the standard you know
when they're very common words like soul
that that when you're talking to
somebody you know say a religious person
and you're trying to explain this
version that first of all you have to
keep the new definition in your head and
had it can cause confusion when talking
to a person or try to communicate these
ideas and verses you know coming up with
say a new word that may have the same
root is soul but that so that keeps the
link so it keeps the association is it
as with religio but it but it's clearly
a new word so it helps separate in our
minds yeah yeah I think that's right I
think the trouble I have is that I get
criticism on the other side of too many
neologism by the way for those of you
who know I'm working very hard in the
transcription for awakening from the
meeting crisis the book I'm working on
I'm also with Madeline creating an
extensive glossary that will have all of
these terms explicate it and explain so
Brett I kind of feel myself internal I'm
handling it well it kind of feels like
I've caught between you know introducing
too many new terms which then people say
that you know it's getting lost in the
neologism and then also but your point I
think is also X
that you know when I when I'm trying to
reinvent you aeternam you know people
are going to they're going to gonna
engage in a kind of equivocation that
I'm actually affording could could be
which is something that I you know I
definitely want to challenge and I'm not
you know I'm not quite sure how to solve
that problem so what I try to do is you
know I try to when I was doing the way
to reinvent here with Paul I'm trying to
pick a term right and I'm trying to
reinvent you in terms of functionality
of new terms so that's why I was linking
the soul to the mortise and suchness
which is not traditional you know
Christian terminology and I'm hoping
that if I can make that Association
strong enough I can sort of get the best
of both maybe avoid both both problems I
don't know if I'm succeeding enough so
what I'm trying to say is I use a term
it's not a particularly the term isn't a
new term it's reinvent Co so people can
say oh it's a neologism but then I link
it to new terms in terms of trying to
explicate you know well are we capturing
or a reinvent EO of its functionality
but sorry I'm hesitating because I'm
really I'm really I'm really taking
apart the points you're making do you
see the point of time to say that's what
I was explicitly doing with Paul I was
bringing out an old term so it wouldn't
be oh here's just another Verve a key
term getting loaded on to us right you
know he's John's connecting up with a
you know a long-standing tradition
there's a set of problems that people
were wrestling with when they wrestled
with that so I could put my finger on
that but then I'm connecting it to like
new terms that haven't been used before
so I'm dislocating it from its normal
semantic network and they're bought but
they're by trying to avoid avoiding
people falling into equivocation and
that's that's why I also kept saying you
know I'm giving a secular version of
this you know
turn anyways that's what I was trying to
do with that that's what I was finding
yeah if I could stand up in defense of
type 1 and type 2 errors perhaps a
moment I think maybe something that it
does is it when we may be getting one of
these terms incorrect is that it forces
us to go into a searching mode where we
we have like a minor aporia perhaps
where we we have to make sense of this
this dual sensing in this overlap or or
disjunction and in that process we come
to look for a deeper understanding and
what the person is intending and that's
actually seems to be quite useful in the
conversational space that's helpful
Thank You Fred I'm interested also
feedback from you I was trying to like
to give you a response are trying to
tell you how I'm wrestling with the
problem that you're putting your finger
off yeah I can I certainly see the
problem I you know I can just also you
know especially as as this movement you
know sort of grows and we try to sort of
popularize these you know I can foresee
sort of pushback by by by certain groups
that you know about co-opting terms and
so on and I and that that can cause
dissonance I mean I out in my my
preference and I think people in the
form of different preferences is is the
new word with a similar route like a
religious example that keeps that keeps
the connection in a very real way it's
very apparent but it's still very
different so that's my preference
personally but others may have may have
may have different preferences no no I
think that's good the problem I wrestled
with that is the root words that we
translate a soul you know they come you
know you get it psyche and you get
drafter to get Numa which is all it's
all this book there's all these
breathing stuff and you know I'm not
quite I don't know what was doing it or
not but but I take your point really
well that is the optimal strategy you
could go back to the connection but then
make it as a base of you thank you great
I know it's 7:30 so I think we're
probably at the end of our hour I just
note you you have so this weekend is the
rebel wisdom it's a free online free
online conference and I think you're
you're going to be speaking did you want
to give a little preview of what you're
going to be talking about some kind of
workshop the details around dialectic
Indian logos and then there's going to
be sort of discussion forum
with myself and Nora Bateson on the
topic of wisdom so those are the three
things I'll be involved in I probably
get involved with some other talks by
some other people and you know let's
trouble with things like that but those
are the three main things
okay well thank you thank you so much
for coming by these sessions are great
and I know I know there's there's
there's never enough time to ask all the
questions but the the good news is that
you'll be back in two weeks time I think
I think our regular time now will be
what six six six clocks at flatland yeah
yeah you know it's a holiday Monday of
some time I'll be here every two weeks
at 6 o'clock to do this I find this very
valuable not only in terms of community
building but I find this very valuable
if the questions really help me think
and this you know this is the core of
dialectic right you know not thinking
before speaking
not speaking without thinking but
thinking in speaking and speaking in
thinking find that just tremendously
helpful so I want to thank everybody for
all the really great questions and again
I I'd like the panorama you know we move
from very practical to you know very
metaphysical philosophical that this is
just excellent even methodological look
we were doing towards the app this is
all tremendously helpful for me so thank
you guys and everyone thank you so much
everyone for coming thank you so much
for that for always setting this up it's
a pleasure
ok so I'm trying to remember how do I be
now so there's a little phone with an X
you'll see just at the bottom of the of
the left-hand panel and so you can
that's the disconnect yeah I see thank
you take care of you see to see yes
thank you I'll see all of you here you
all I guess that's right for here you
all in two weeks from now take care
everyone thanks so much yeah
all right everyone bye bye John